Guide to the John Downey Works Papers, 1911-1928
Department of Special Collections
John Downey Works Papers,
1911-1928
Special Collections M031
Works, John Downey
2 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions:
None.
Provenance:
Gift of Lewis R. Works, 1930-31.
BIOGRAPHY
John Downey Works was born March 29, 1847 on a farm in Ohio County, Indiana. Educated in the common schools of the state until 1861, he then served eighteen months with the U. S. Volunteers in the Civil War. In 1868, he married Alice Banta, was admitted to the bar, and began a law practice in Vevay, Indiana which lasted for fifteen years. In 1879, he was elected to the Indiana House of Representatives for one term. Forced to leave Indiana in l883 due to ill health, Works and his family journeyed West and settled in southern California where, from 1886-87, he served as Judge of the Superior Court of San Diego County, Los Angeles. In 1888, he was appointed to fill a vacancy as Associate Justice of the Supreme Court of the State of California and shortly thereafter, was elected to fill out the term. Works returned to a private legal partnership in 1891 and remained so engaged until 1910 when he served for a brief time as President of the City Council of Los Angeles. In 1911, he was nominated by the Progressive Republicans of the Lincoln-Roosevelt League for the position of U. S. Senator, was subsequently elected, and served in Congress until 1917 when he returned once again to private life and practice. Works died on June 6, 1928.
Among Works' publications are:
Indiana Pleading and Practice (1883)
Water and Water Rights (1890)
Courts and their Jurisdiction (1894)
What's Wrong With the World (1922)
Man's Duty to Man (1923)
Juridical Reform (1924)
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The Works Papers include the correspondence of John Downey Works dated from 1911 to 1928, the bulk of which was written between 1916 and 1926. In addition, the collection contains a typescript copy of Works' memoirs concerning, especially, his years in the U. S. Senate, several typescripts of articles and speeches, and a scrapbook of newspaper clippings by or about Works from 1906-1911. Also included are printed copies of many of Works' Senate speeches.
Of primary interest in the Papers is the correspondence concerning Works' election to the U. S. Senate in 1911, publication of his several books, and his relationship with the Church of Christ Scientist.
For additional information consult the Works Collection in the Bancroft Library, University of California (see correspondence to Works from J. C. Rowell, Librarian). Also helpful for general reference is Irene Lucile Way's The Political Career of John Downey Works, a thesis written 1929-30 at Stanford University for the degree of Master of Arts.
MAJOR CORRESPONDENTS
Blight, Reynold E.; Christian Science Monitor; Hargraves, John W.; La Follette., Robert M.; Neale Publishing Co.; Patton, Charles 0.; Stratford Co.; Taft, William H.; Rowell, Chester H.
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- Correspondence: Letters of John Downey Works, Jan. 1911 to May 1928 (Box 1)
  Arranged chronologically
- Correspondence: Letters to John Downey Works. (Box 2)
  Also includes letters about Works and extensive cross-references.
  Arranged alphabetically by signer or author and chronologically under each signer
- Miscellany (Box 3)
  Memoirs of John Downey Works, typescripts of some speeches and articles, formal photographs, and scrapbook of newspaper clippings by or about Works.
- Speeches, 1911-1919 (Box 4)
  Printed copies of U. S. Senate and miscellaneous speeches by John Downey Works.
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence: Letters of John Downey Works
  - Jan. 14, 1911-Jan. 17, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jan. 18, 1911-Feb. 1, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - July 5, 1916-Nov. 13, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - March 5. 1917-Nov. 19, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Feb. 6. l9l8-Dec. 27, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 5:)
  - Jan. 8, 1919-Dec. 30, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jan. 15, 1920-Dec. 27., 1920 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - March 24, 1921-Dec. 30., 1921 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jan. 16, 1922-Dec. 19, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jan. 2, 1923-Dec. 19, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Jan. 3, 1924-Nov. 7, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jan. 8, 1925-Nov. 13, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Feb. 8, 1926-Dec. 10, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Jan. 31, 1927-Dec. 7, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Jan. 27, 1928-May 31, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Correspondence: Letters to John Downey Works
  - Alberti-Ayers (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Backus-Burritt (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Carlson-Currier (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Daniels-Griffith (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Hahn-Hutton (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Jacobs-Luce (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - MacMillan-Murphy (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - National-Neale (Dec. 1918) (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Neale (Jan. 1919-Dec. 1919) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Neale (Jan. 1920)-Norton (Box 2, Folder 25:)
  - Obrien-Putnam's Sons (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Reed-Rush (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Savage-Sword (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Taft-Young (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Miscellaneous unidentified- 1911 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Letters about Works
    - Barrows-Works (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Miscellany
  - Some of my Experiences in Political and Official Life - the memoirs of John Downey Works. (Box 3, Folder 32:)
  - Typescript copies of several speeches and articles by John Downey Works. (Box 3, Folder 33:)
  - 26 formal photographs of John Downey Works as U. S. Senator. (Box 3, Folder 34:)
  - Scrapbook (labeled) of newspaper clippings by or about John Downey Works, 1906-11. (Shelf On shelf)
- Speeches
  - Printed copies of Senate Speeches (U.S.) by John Downey Works (Box 4)
    - Initiative, Referendum and Recall, April 20, 1911, 5 copies
    - Proposed Department of Health, July 6, 1911, 8 copies
    - To Establish an Independent Health Service, April 29, 30, 1912, 2 copies
    - The Presidential Term, Dec. 9, 10, 1912, 13 copies
    - Clean and Reliable Journalism, Apr. 17, 1913, 5 copies
    - Trusts and Combinations, May 5, 1913, 8 copies
    - An Amendment ot the Constitution Prohibiting the Sale, Manufacture and Importation of Distilled Liquor, June 21, 1913, 5 copies
    - Tariff on California Products, July 24, 25, 1913, 4 copies
    - San Francisco Water Supply, Dec. 2, 3, 1913, 4 copies
    - Bill to Repeal Hetch Hetchy Grant, Dec. 20, 1913, 3 copies
    - Patronage, Jan. 26, 914, 5 copies
    - Cooperative Agricultural Extension Work, Jan. 30, 1914, 5 copies
    - One Year of Democratic Rule, Mar. 6, 1914, 8 copies
    - Treaty Relations with Great Britain and Panama Canal Tolls, Apr. 7, 8, 1914, 1 copy
    - Affairs in Mexico, Apr. 21, 1914, 5 copies
    - Trust Legislation, July 17, 1914, 5 copies
    - Development of Water Power, Feb. 2, 1915, 2 copies
    - Preparedness for National Defense, Dec. 16, 1915, 5 copies
    - Preparedness for Peace, Mar. 23, 1916, 5 copies
    - National Preparedness - Judges in Politics, Apr. 12, 1916, 5 copies
    - Good Roads - Misappropriation of Public Funds, Apr. 21, 1916, 5 copies
    - Americanism and Preparedness for National Defense, Jun. 26, 1916, 5 copies
    - The Asiatic Problem, July 14, 1916, 4 copies
    - Naval Appropriations, July 17, 1916, 5 copies
    - Downward Tendencies of Government and Citizenship, Jan. 4,5, 1917, 7 copies
    - Our Relations with Germany, Feb. 7, 1917, 5 copies
    - On Authorizing the President to Arm Merchant Ships, Mar. 4, 1917, 1 copy
  - Miscellaneous speeches and articles
    - Health address of Works to the National League for Medical Freedom, Nov. 24, 1911, 3 copies
    - Expense of Public Health and Medical Service - letter from secretary of Treasury, Jan. 6, 1913, 1 copy
    - "War, Business and Peace," - Address to Commercial Law League of America, Aug. 5, 1915, 1 copy
    - "Works defends war stand," - article in The New American Woman, July 1917, 2 copies
    - Review of Work's book on Juridical Reform - by Roscoe Pound in Harvard Law Review, Dec. 1919, 1 copy